<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Paris relation of the Battel of Landen, July 29th, 1693, between the French, commanded by the D. of Luxemburg, and the confederates, by the K. of Great Britain publish'd by the French King's authority, with his letter, ordering the Archbishop of Paris to sing Te Deum, and a private letter from a very good hand in Paris, with another account of the battel : as also reflexions upon the King's letter, by a very learned French pen and observations by another hand here, proving the French king and his gazeteers account to be inconsistent with themselves, and one another, as well as contrary to truth, and that though the French kept the field, yet they were really loosers by the action.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55961</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13087448</idno>
  <idno type="VID">97313</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240856587</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5965</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13087448</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55961)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 747:45)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Paris relation of the Battel of Landen, July 29th, 1693, between the French, commanded by the D. of Luxemburg, and the confederates, by the K. of Great Britain publish'd by the French King's authority, with his letter, ordering the Archbishop of Paris to sing Te Deum, and a private letter from a very good hand in Paris, with another account of the battel : as also reflexions upon the King's letter, by a very learned French pen and observations by another hand here, proving the French king and his gazeteers account to be inconsistent with themselves, and one another, as well as contrary to truth, and that though the French kept the field, yet they were really loosers by the action.</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1643-1715 : Louis XIV)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Rhodes ..., and J. Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published for undeceiving the publick, who are so much abus'd for seditious relations."</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: prelim. p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Luxembourg, François-Henri de Montmorency, --  duc de, 1628-1695.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Landen, Battle of, 1693.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History, Military --  1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97313:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97313:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Paris Relation</hi> OF THE Battel of Landen, <hi>JƲLY</hi> 29<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> 1693, Between the <hi>French,</hi> Commanded by the D. of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> And the <hi>Confederates,</hi> by the K. of <hi>Great Britain; Publish'd by the French King's Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH His LETTER, Ordering the Archbishop of <hi>Paris</hi> to sing <hi>Te Deum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND A <hi>Private Letter</hi> from a very good Hand in <hi>Paris,</hi> with another Account of the Battel.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO <hi>Reflexions</hi> upon the King's Letter, by a very Learned French Pen.</p>
            <p>AND <hi>Observations</hi> by another Hand here, Proving the <hi>French King</hi> and his <hi>Gazeteers</hi> Account to be inconsistent with themselves, and one another, as well as contrary to Truth: And that though the <hi>French</hi> kept the Field, yet they were really Loosers by the Action.</p>
            <p>Publish'd for Vndeceiving the Publick, who are so much Abus'd by Seditious Relations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Rhodes,</hi> at the <hi>Star,</hi> the Corner of <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane, Fleet-street:</hi> And <hi>I. Harris,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow,</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:97313:2"/>
            <p>This may be Printed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aug. 26. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>EDWARD COOKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <head>There is lately Published,</head>
            <p>AN Exact Relation of the Battel of <hi>Landen,</hi> July 29. 1693. between the Army of the <hi>Confederates,</hi> Commanded by the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and that of the <hi>French</hi> King, under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg.</hi> With His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Letter to the <hi>States-General,</hi> from his Head Quarters at <hi>Eppegem,</hi> Aug. 12. 1693. With a Description of the Order of Battel, in a Copper-Plate. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Rhodes,</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet:</hi> And <hi>J. Harris,</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:97313:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AFter so many Falsifications made by the <hi>French,</hi> as King <hi>William</hi>'s Death and Defeat at the <hi>Boyne,</hi> which gave them a Sham Subject of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph throughout their Kingdom; their huge Victory which they pretended to have had over us at <hi>Tinmouth,</hi> and others of the like sort, it might reasonably be thought unnecessary to prove them Liars at any time after; but their Mercenary Scriblers at Home, and their Pensioners and Bigotted Well-Wishers Abroad, having Magnified their Late Victory beyond all manner of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, contrary both to Reason and good Sense; We hope it will not be unacceptable
<pb facs="tcp:97313:3"/> to the Publick, that we have Exhibited a Faithfull Translation of the <hi>Paris</hi> Account, and the <hi>French</hi> King's Letter, the very reading of which is sufficient to Confute them; but for the V;ndeceiving of all well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning People, even those of Ordinary Capacities, there are Reflexions added to prove the Falshood of what the <hi>French</hi> and their Friends assert, and by Comparing of Our Account with Theirs, I doubt not but it will be found as demonstrable as any thing of that nature can be, that their Loss can be probably little less than 20000, and ours not much above 6000; for the Proof of which, We referr to the following Account and Reflexions.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97313:3"/>
            <head>THE RELATION OF THE VICTORY Obtain'd over the CONFEDERATES At <hi>Nerwinde,</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> by the King's Army COMMANDED By the D. of <hi>Luxemburgh.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Faithfully Translated from the Original, Printed in the <hi>Louvre,</hi> by the <hi>Paris</hi> Gazetteer: With the King's Authority. <hi>Aug.</hi> 12. 1693.</head>
            <p n="1">(1.) IMmediately after the taking of the Town, and Castle of <hi>Huy,</hi> the D. of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> went to view the Intrenchments which the Enemies had made before <hi>Liege;</hi> and being informed that the Confederates Army was return'd to encamp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the little River of <hi>Geete,</hi> and the Brook of <hi>Lande</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97313:4"/>
               <hi>Fermé;</hi> and that on the News of his March, they had weakned themselves by sending Ten Battalions to <hi>Liege,</hi> he resolved to attack them, according to the King's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to find them out, and give them Battel.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) But the better to cover his Design, he commanded his Troops to amass a vast quantity of <hi>Fascines,</hi> as if he had designed to march for <hi>Liege.</hi> He intended to have broke up on the 27th. of <hi>July</hi> in the Evening, but a great Rain (which lasted all that Day, and most part of the Night) oblig'd him to deferr it till the next Day: So that on the 28th. about Five in the Morning, he left his Camp at <hi>Hellich,</hi> which was Seven Leagues from the Enemy, and marching in Four Columns, the Infantry in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and the Cavalry on the wings, he passed the <hi>Jarr</hi> near its Spring-head, betwixt the Villages of <hi>Borchiworm,</hi> and <hi>Latine. Luxemburgh</hi> himself was at the head of the Left Wing, which in this March composed the Column on the Right; and arriving at the Mill of <hi>Warem,</hi> he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood by his Scout, that the Enemy continued in the same Camp. When he made a halt to give the Column time to pass the Defile of the <hi>Jarr,</hi> and committing them to the Conduct of the Mareschal <hi>de Joyeuse,</hi> he put himself at the head of the Right Wing, commanded by the Duke <hi>de Villeroy,</hi> who was advanced between <hi>Lens-les-Beguines,</hi> and <hi>Avernas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) While the Infantry passed the <hi>Jarr,</hi> under the command of the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> the Sieur <hi>Rubantel,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Barwick,</hi> Lieutenant-Generals, upon several Bridges made for that end, <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> advanced at the head of the King's Houshold, followed by the rest of the Columne, and made hast to come in view of the Enemy, designing either to keep them in their Camp, or charge their Rear, if they endeavoured to re-pass the River. About Four in the Afternoon he arrived near the Village of <hi>Racou,</hi> and forthwith put Two Regiments of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons into the Villages of St. <hi>Gertrude,</hi> and <hi>Hautwinde,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97313:4"/> backing them with the Battalions which were designed for the Lines, under the conduct of the Count <hi>de Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chevreuil,</hi> Lieutenant-General, who having encamp'd that Day a-part from the Left of the Army, was farther advanced than the rest of the Foot.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) On the appearance of this Body, the Confederate Generals being perswaded, that the D. of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> had still a Design upon <hi>Liege,</hi> they could not believe that the whole Army was marching toward them, but supposed it to be only a Detachment sent by the Mareschal, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his March; but the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> mounting on Horseback, quickly discovered the truth, and put their Forces immediataly in Battel-Array at the head of their Camp.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Mareschal <hi>Joyeuse</hi> arrived with the Left Wing at Six a Clock; and the Infantry, which the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> had caused to march from the Passage of the <hi>Jarr</hi> in Four Columnes, for the greater dispatch, arrived at Eight a Clock with a great part of the Artillery.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) It being then too late to Engage, the D. of <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburgh</hi> contented himself to put his Troops in order; for which end he commanded the Marquis <hi>de Crequi,</hi> Mareschal <hi>de Camp,</hi> to possess the Village of <hi>Lande Fermé,</hi> with his Right, and the Brigades of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urbon,</hi> and <hi>Lyon,</hi> to whom the Marquis <hi>de Feuquiers,</hi> Lieutenant-General, join'd that of <hi>Maulevrier:</hi> With these Brigades, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt that Village, and St. <hi>Gertrude,</hi> he posted those of <hi>Navarre, Anjou</hi> and <hi>Arras,</hi> conducted by the Count <hi>de Solre,</hi> Mareschal <hi>de Camp,</hi> with the Dragoons of <hi>Caylus, Finmarcon,</hi> and the Two Regiments of <hi>Asfeld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">(7.) To the Left, he ordered the Sieur <hi>de Rubantel,</hi> and the D. of <hi>Barwick</hi> Lieutenant-Generals; the Baron <hi>de Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sley,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Lucan,</hi> Mareschals <hi>de Camp,</hi> with the King's Brigade, those of <hi>Piedmont, Crussol, Orleance</hi> and <hi>Reynold</hi> which join'd them of <hi>Salis,</hi> and <hi>Arbouville,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97313:5"/> that were already posted in the Village of <hi>Haute-Winde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Betwixt those Two Villages, thus possessed by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry, the D. of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> caused a Line of Cavalry to be form'd, consisting of Seven Squadrons of the King's Houshold, with the Regiment of the <hi>Camp-Master-General,</hi> the <hi>Dauphin</hi>'s Foreign Regiment, and that of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> having at their head, to the right, the D. <hi>de Villeroy,</hi> with the Sieur <hi>Rosen,</hi> Lieutenant-General, the D. <hi>de Roque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laire,</hi> Mareschal <hi>de Camp;</hi> and to the left, the Mareschal <hi>de Joyeuse,</hi> the D. of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> Lieutenant-General, and the Count <hi>de Marsin,</hi> Mareschal <hi>de Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">(9.) He formed a Second Line, consisting of the <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Swisse</hi> Guards, and those of <hi>Guiche,</hi> commanded by the Prince of <hi>Conti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">(10.) He formed a Third with the rest of the King's Houshold, the Brigade of <hi>Bolen,</hi> the <hi>Carabineers,</hi> and <hi>Pras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> Regiment, having at their head, the Marquis <hi>de Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiers,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>de Buscha,</hi> Lieutenant-Generals, the D. <hi>d'Elbaeuf,</hi> and the Count <hi>de Nassaw,</hi> Mareschals <hi>de Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">(11.) Then he Composed a Fourth, consisting of the Brigades of <hi>Vermandois, Zurbeck, Zurlaube, Nice, Royal Roussilon,</hi> and <hi>La Sarre,</hi> with the rest of the Cavalry, Commanded by the Sieur <hi>de Vatteville</hi> Lieutenant-General, who formed also other Lines, according as the Ground would allow. All the Cavalry were put in order by the Duke <hi>de Chartres,</hi> who Commanded them.</p>
            <p n="12">(12.) The Chevalier de <hi>Bezons,</hi> Mareshal <hi>de Camp</hi> was posted with a Reserve behind the Village of <hi>Haute-Winde,</hi> and the Sieurs de X <hi>menes</hi> and <hi>Pracontal,</hi> with some Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gades of Horse, drawn from the Right and Leit, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so placed there.</p>
            <p n="13">(13.) The Army passed the Night thus in Battle Array, and in the mean time, the Enemies did Fortifie themselves with all possible Diligence.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97313:5"/>(14.) On the 29<hi>th.</hi> by break of day, we perceived the <hi>Confederates</hi> also in Order of Battel, having on their Right the Villages of <hi>Laer</hi> and <hi>Nerwinde,</hi> which they had In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench'd, and possessed with a great Body of Foot: Their Left reacht to the Brook of <hi>Landen,</hi> along which, they were posted towards <hi>Leewe,</hi> and they had cast up a Great Entrenchment before them, upon the height, from the Village of <hi>Nether-Landen</hi> to <hi>Nerwinde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">(15.) Behind that Retrenchment, which was Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Eighty Pieces of Cannon; their Infantry was posted, sustain'd by Two Lines of Cavalry, and having also on their Right, from their Entrenchment, to the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Geet,</hi> Three other Lines of Cavalry, facing towards the Villages of <hi>Laer</hi> and <hi>Nerwinde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">(16.) About half an hour past Four in the Morning, the Cannon began to Play on both sides, and continued till the Fight was over.</p>
            <p n="17">(17.) The Duke of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> having viewed the Posture of the Enemy, judg'd, that it behov'd him in the first place, to make himself Master of the Villages of <hi>Laer</hi> and <hi>Nerwinde,</hi> on which he conceiv'd the Success of the Battel to depend; and therefore, order'd the Attack upon the latter, at 8 a Clock.</p>
            <p n="18">(18.) The Sieur de <hi>Rubantel</hi> Commanded the Right of that Attack, with the Brigades of the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Crus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sol;</hi> The Count de <hi>Montchevril,</hi> that of the Left, with the Brigades of <hi>Salis</hi> and <hi>Arbouville;</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> that of the middle, with the Brigades of <hi>Piedmont</hi> and <hi>Orleans;</hi> and those Three Lieutenant Generals had under them the Baron de <hi>Bressey,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Lucan,</hi> Mareschals <hi>de Camp.</hi> The Sieur <hi>Reynold</hi> at the same time, had Orders to make himself Master of the Village of <hi>Laer,</hi> with his Brigade, and a Regiment of Dragoons▪ The Sieurs de <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>menes</hi> and <hi>Prac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntal,</hi> with the Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97313:6"/> Line, and the Chevalier de <hi>Bezons,</hi> with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, being Commanded to sustain him.</p>
            <p n="19">(19.) The Village of <hi>Nerwinde</hi> we carried with a great deal of Vigour; but the Enemy returning with fresh Troops, regain'd it after a long and bloody Fight: However, they were not long there, till they were Attack'd by the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade of <hi>Guiche;</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Bourbon</hi> at their Head, who retook the Village, and beat the Enemy into the Valley, where their Cannon was planted: but the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> having immediately detach'd new Troops, and used his utmost Efforts, to repossess himself of that Village, which was of so much Import and Consequence to him, we were obliged to retire again to the uttermost Hedges of the Village, and the like befel our other Troops, which had taken the Village of <hi>Laer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">(20.) While we were Masters of these two Posts, the Sieur de <hi>Pracontal,</hi> with the Brigade of <hi>Montrevel,</hi> and the Chevalier de <hi>Bezons,</hi> with the Reserve, found means to enter as far as the Plain, and to defeat one of the Enemies Lines, but not being sustain'd soon enough, because of the Defiles, they were obliged after several Charges, to retire to their first Post.</p>
            <p n="21">(21.) While these things past on the Left, the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> seized the Hedges before the Village of <hi>Lande Fermé,</hi> with the Brigade which had pass'd the night on that side; and advancing further with the four Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Dragoons, order'd to march on the other side of the Brook of <hi>Landen,</hi> they push'd the Enemy to the Flank of their Retrenchments.</p>
            <p n="22">(22.) The Marquis de <hi>Crequi,</hi> perceiving the Battel grew hot, sustain'd his Dragoons by the Brigades of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre, Bourbon, Lion, Anjou</hi> and <hi>Arras.</hi> And the Prince de <hi>Conti,</hi> who was at the Center of the Line, marching up to the Attack as soon as it began, the Enemies were beat from Post to Post, and we became Masters of part of their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97313:6"/> Entrenchments. But the Duke de <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>schal de <hi>Villeroy,</hi> and Prince de <hi>Conti,</hi> having viewed the Ground, and found a great Ditch full of Water, which it was impossible for the Cavalry to pass, did not think fit to push that Attack any farther, but contented themselves to keep the Posts which they had taken.</p>
            <p n="23">(23.) The Duke de <hi>Luxemburg</hi> returning to the Left, carried the Brigade of Guards with him to the Village of <hi>Nerwinde,</hi> resolving to make his last Effort upon the Place. The Prince de <hi>Conti,</hi> put himself at the Head of the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade; and while those of <hi>Zurbeck</hi> and <hi>Zurlaube</hi> entred by the Left of the Village; he forced it on the Right, chas'd the Enemy entirely from thence, and maintain'd himself there against all their Endeavours to repossess themselves, and the five Brigades of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> the Kings, and those of <hi>Crussol, Guiche,</hi> and <hi>Orleans,</hi> rallying themselves, entred at the same time.</p>
            <p n="24">(24.) At that very Moment, the Mareschal de <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburg,</hi> went to view the Enemies Entrenchments on the Right of the Village, and there he found a Passage, where not above two Horsemen could pass in Front, and the Duke de <hi>Villeroy</hi> having undertaken to pass the same with the Cavalry under his Command, <hi>Luxemburg</hi> went to the Left, to seek out some other Passages.</p>
            <p n="25">(25.) The Duke de <hi>Villeroy,</hi> with all possible Diligence advanc'd five Squadrons of the King's Houshold, who defiling to the Right, and marching the Columne back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, entred the Retrenchment; the Light-Horse first, the <hi>Gens d' Arms</hi> next, and Three Squadrons of the Guards <hi>de Corps</hi> last.</p>
            <p n="26">(26.) The Enemies were so near, that those five Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, had scarce ground enough to put themselves in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by stretching a little to the Left: In the mean time, perceiving the Enemies begin to move toward them, they Charged them briskly, and broke through all that was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97313:7"/> in their way, but being at last over-powered by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies whole Line, they were obliged to retire, and rally under the Fire of the Infantry. It was on this Occasion, that the Duke de <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rires,</hi> who charg'd at their Head, was now encompass'd by the Enemy, but fought his way out at last with a great deal of Valour, having many of his men killed and wounded on each hand of him.</p>
            <p n="27">(27.) At the same time, the Duke de <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found a Passage betwixt the <hi>King</hi>'s Brigade, and that of <hi>Zurbeck,</hi> He, and the Prince de <hi>Conti,</hi> with the Count <hi>de Marsin,</hi> entred also into the Plane, at the head of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabineers, and many other Regiments, while the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>schal <hi>de Joyeuse,</hi> and the Duke de <hi>Bourbon,</hi> who had po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted himself again at the head of his Wing of Horse, did pass with the Count de <hi>Nassaw,</hi> betwixt the Villages of <hi>Nerwinde,</hi> and that of <hi>Laer,</hi> with the <hi>Camp-Masters</hi> Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade, that of <hi>Royal Roussilon,</hi> and the <hi>Cuirassiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">(28.) The Sieur <hi>Ximenes,</hi> Count <hi>de Guiscard,</hi> the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>de Bezons,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>Pracontal</hi> passed on their Left, along the Hedges of the Village of <hi>Laer,</hi> with part of the Second Line, and the Reserve. The Marquis <hi>de Harcourt,</hi> who had march'd from <hi>Huy</hi> at the noise of the Cannon, with the 22 Squadrons under his Command, to take share of the Honour, and Danger of the Day, made part of his Dragoons to alight, beat the Enemies from the Village of <hi>Laer,</hi> and not only entred into the said Village, but also into the <hi>Morasse,</hi> betwixt it and the River <hi>Geete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">(29.) Our Troops on the Right of <hi>Nerwinde</hi> had equal Success, the Brigades of <hi>Vermandois, Nice, Roussilon,</hi> and <hi>Sarre,</hi> having fill'd up some part of the Enemies En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments, the Duke <hi>de Villeroy,</hi> with the Sieur <hi>Rosen,</hi> the Marquis de <hi>Feuquieres,</hi> the Sieur de <hi>Busca,</hi> and the Duke de <hi>Roquelaure,</hi> made the rest of the Troops of the King's Houshold pass there.</p>
            <p n="30">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97313:7"/>(30.) On their Right, the Duke de <hi>Elbaeuf</hi> entred with the Brigade of <hi>Bolen,</hi> followed by the Sieur de <hi>Vatteville,</hi> with part of the second Line on the Right, and the Duke de <hi>Montmorenci,</hi> who having followed his Father the Duke de <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> during the whole Action, did then take his Post of Mareschal <hi>de Camp,</hi> and put himself at the Head of the Brigades of <hi>Rottembourg,</hi> and <hi>Presle,</hi> with which he defeated several of the Enemies Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons; and amongst others, the Regiments of <hi>Galloway,</hi> where we are inform'd, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> fought in Person.</p>
            <p n="31">(31.) All the Cavalry being passed, there were many Charges on both sides, with a great deal of Courage and Obstinacy, and the Duke de <hi>Luxemburg</hi> riding perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from the Right to the Left, did form most of the Squadrons himself, and Lead them on to the Charge.</p>
            <p n="32">(32.) The Duke de <hi>Chartres</hi> did as much on his side, and did Animate all by his Presence and Example.</p>
            <p n="33">(33.) The Mareschal de <hi>Villeroy</hi> at the Head of the Right, gave all possible Marks of his Experience, and Courage.</p>
            <p n="34">(34.) The Prince de <hi>Conti,</hi> who had already Charg'd with the Carabineers, Charg'd again with the King's <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadiers,</hi> at which time he receiv'd a Wound in his Head with a Faulchion, which yet did not hinder his Pursuit of the Enemy, having first killed the Horse-man who gave him the said Wound.</p>
            <p n="35">(35.) The Mareschal de <hi>Joyeuse,</hi> tho' also wounded in the beginning of the Battel by a Musquet Shot in the Thigh, signaliz'd himself in several Charges, with the Troops on the Left which he Commanded.</p>
            <p n="36">(36.) Into that same Wing the Duke de <hi>Bourbon</hi> with his usual Courage, did often throw himself upon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and Charge them with Advantage. In fine, the General and Subalterne Officers, as well as the private Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinels,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97313:8"/> performing each their part with Bravery and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution, the Enemies were forced to yield to the Valour and Number of the King's Troops.</p>
            <p n="37">(37.) Their Right being broke by the Marquis d' <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court,</hi> the Sieur de <hi>Ximenes,</hi> and the Chevalier de <hi>Bezons,</hi> was driven head-long into the <hi>Geete,</hi> which in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces was filled with an infinite number of Men, and Horse, kill'd, or drown'd.</p>
            <p n="38">(38.) Their Left made no longer stand, so that there was Confusion among them throughout, and there were only 10 or 12 Squadrons, and 2 or 3 Battalions, which being furthest advanced in their Retreat, got out of our sight, and escaped without our being able to Charge them.</p>
            <p n="39">(39.) The King's Troops remain'd Masters of the Field, with 76 pieces of the Enemies Cannon, 8 Mortars, many Pontons, and generally all the Epiquage of their Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Ammunition. We took also 66 Standards, 22 Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, 12 pair of Kettle-Drums, and 1500 Prisoners, 200 of them being Officers and amongst others, THE COUNT DE <hi>SOLMES,</hi> Lieutenant General, the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Captain of the Prince of <hi>Orange'</hi>s Guards, and Lieutenant-General, the Sieur de <hi>Zeuleystein,</hi> another Lieutenant-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the Count de <hi>Broway,</hi> Serjeant Major of the Battel, the Count de <hi>Lippe,</hi> and many other Colonels.</p>
            <p n="40">(40.) All the Advices from the Enemies Country say, that their Loss exceeds 20000 Men.</p>
            <p n="41">(41.) In the King's Army we reckon 2000 men kill'd, and 3 or 4000 wounded: The Officers which we have lost, are the Count de <hi>Monchevrevil,</hi> Lieutenant-General, the Duke de <hi>V;ses,</hi> Prince <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> Son to the Prince of <hi>Lislebonne,</hi> the Count de <hi>Gassion,</hi> the Marquis de <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallon,</hi> the Count de <hi>Montrevel,</hi> the Sieur de <hi>Lignery,</hi> the Sieur de <hi>Bolen,</hi> the Chavalier <hi>Rosen,</hi> the Sieur de <hi>Chastenay,</hi> the Sieur <hi>Gaujac,</hi> the Sieur de <hi>Vaurouy,</hi> Captains of the Guards, the Sieur de <hi>La Cosle,</hi> and some others.</p>
            <p n="42">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97313:8"/>(42.) The Duke de <hi>Bourbon</hi> received several Wounds in his Arms, the Duke de <hi>Luxemburgh'</hi>s Horse was also wounded, as were several of his People about him, the Duke de <hi>Montmorenci,</hi> and the Count de <hi>Luxe,</hi> his Sons were also wounded; the first on the Shoulder, and the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Leg. The Prince de <hi>Conti,</hi> and the Duke de <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy,</hi> had each a Horse killed under them, with the same Cannon-Ball: the Duke de <hi>Roche-Guyon</hi> was wounded in the Foot, the Marquis de <hi>Villequier,</hi> and the Marquis de <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefort,</hi> my Lord <hi>Lucan,</hi> the Chevalier <hi>de Sillery,</hi> the Sieur de <hi>Tracy,</hi> and the Sieur de <hi>Saillant,</hi> Captain of the Guards, and many others, were also wounded.</p>
            <p n="43">(43.) After this great Victory, so glorious to the King's Arms, the greatest part of the Enemies Troops threw down their Weapons, that they might the better escape the pursuit of the Conquerours, so that all the Fields and Ways, till they came to such places where they thought themselves in safety, were strew'd with Arms; and the Remains of their Army were so scattered, that they have not hitherto been able to rally them.</p>
            <p n="44">(44.) In fine, The Loss which the <hi>Allies</hi> suffered in this Memorable Battel, together with the taking of <hi>Heidleberg, Roses,</hi> and <hi>Huy,</hi> and the greatest part of the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch Smirna</hi> Fleets, makes it evident, that God always favours the Justice of the King's Cause, and that if his Enemies be so blind, as to prefer the Continuance of the War, so fatal to them, before an honourable Peace, his Subjects will at least have the Satisfaction to see his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as well as the Limits of his Kingdom, augmented by his New Conquests; and a Chain of Prosperity, which will sufficiently compensate for whatever they have been obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to Contribute for the <hi>Maintenance</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Good</hi> of the <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97313:9"/>
            <head>The <hi>French King'</hi>s Letter to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Paris,</hi> ordering him to sing <hi>Te Deum,</hi> for the above-mentioned Victory.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COUSIN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Army which my Enemies had in <hi>Flanders,</hi> composed of the choicest of their Troops, and commanded by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in Person, was attacked in their Camp the 29th. of the last Month, by my Cousin the Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh, according to my Order:</hi> The Enemies who had foreseen his Design, omitted nothing that could be done for their own Safety; and although their Camp was very advantageously po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, they did, nevertheless, fortifie the same by <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtable Intrenchments,</hi> and <hi>incredible Labour.</hi> However they were forced, and put to the Rout in the same; <hi>part of their Army being killed on the Spot, part of them drown'd in their flight, and the rest dispersed;</hi> many of their general Officers, and a great Number of others were killed and taken Prisoners; 76 Pieces of Cannon, 8 Mortars, and 9 Pontons, left in the Field of Battel; 12 Pair of Kettle-Drums, 60 Standards, and 22 Colours taken from them by force, or abandoned by those who were breathing out their last. <hi>There is Nothing which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97313:9"/> my Enemies have not Reason to fear after such a terrible Defeat, and Nothing which I have not a Right to hope</hi> for; but I level all my Wishes at the Wellfare of my People, and I desire to reap no other Fruits from such a Glorious Victory, but that <hi>my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies would open their Eyes, perceive their own true Interests, and entertain Thoughts of a solid and durable Peace, which I have always offered them in the midst of my greatest Prosperities.</hi> It is therefore to desire the same from God, and to thank him for so many Favours, that I would have you to cause <hi>Te Deum</hi> to be sung in the Cathedral Church of my good City of <hi>Paris,</hi> on such a day, and hour, as the Grand Master of the Ceremonies shall give you Order from me. Hereupon, Cousin, I pray God to take you into his Holy and Gracious Protection.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Marli,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>August</hi> 7th. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>LOUIS.</signed>
               <signed>Phelypeaux.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97313:10"/>
            <head>The Extract of a Letter writ from <hi>Paris;</hi> with Reflexions upon the <hi>Te Deum.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">WE knew not at first what to think or believe concerning the Battel, the News then brought being Equivocal both as to the Loss and Gain; so that we were doubtful whether we had most reason to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, or to be sorrowful: But the next News did mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie our Advantage, <hi>Joining therewith the Rumour of a Second Action, less Equivocal then the first:</hi> But howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, this did not hold true. In fine, an entire Victory is publish'd by a Letter under the Royal Seal, the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards were carried in Procession, and <hi>Te Deum</hi> sung; so that here was enough for the Publick, and the First<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruit of the Victory which we must not lose. But let's come to Particulars. The Letter is of Mr. <hi>P. R</hi>'s Stile, who had orders to trumpet out our Victory on the highest Note, wherein he hath acquitted himself to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; witness his <hi>Redoubtable Intrenchments,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible Labour, which neverthless, were but the Work of one Night, and must needs have fatigu'd the Enemy before the Battel;</hi> another Evidence is <hi>such a terrible Defeat,</hi> after which he brings the King in declaiming like an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, <hi>There is nothing which my Enemies have not reason to fear, and nothing which I have not reason to hope for.</hi> If this be not enough to frighten the <hi>Allies,</hi> it's their own fault; for this Figure is proper enough for the Purpose, but the King's Design is only that <hi>They may open their Eyes, and perceive their own true Interest,</hi> This is so fine a Turn, that our Court-Zealots have not fallen short of their Devoir, to exalt the Charity of our Monarch, which is so great, <hi>as to make him more sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97313:10"/>
                  <hi>about the true Interests of his Enemies, than they are themselves,</hi> but those who want Faith, in their own Breasts (and you know their Number is great) do very much doubt whether the <hi>All<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> will have enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, or accept of a Peace accommodated by us to their true Interests, which they won't understand, tho' we are willing to beat it into their Brains by <hi>Cannon-Bullets.</hi> Nay these Infidels say, <hi>That the Peace which we demand from God, resembles the Deliverance which</hi> Charles V. <hi>demanded for the Pope, whom he himself did hold in Prison; that is to say, We would have God to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to us, by a durable Peace, what we have taken from our Enemies in Peace, or War, and have no mind to part with.</hi> But farther, we understand, that this Victory in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> though Glorious even to the Superlative Degree, <hi>hath not inspired the Dauphin with Ambition enough to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase another at the same rate, from Prince Lewis of</hi> Baden, <hi>and to try the Second Touch at forcing Entrenchments.</hi> This Letter under Seal, does prudently hide our own Loss, but insists on that of the Enemies. It makes a thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Report with the <hi>Confederate</hi> Cannon, but does not tell us how many Men they cost us: It displays their Ensigns, and Standards with Triumph, but says nothing of those which they have taken from us, tho' more in proportion than what we took from them, because we use fewer in our Battalions and Squadrons than they. That would not have been meet for a <hi>Te Deum;</hi> which is to make Mirth for a Victory, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the People to pay the <hi>Piper,</hi> but not to be wail the Dead, which is the Office of those that manage Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, or sing the <hi>Irish Corronach.</hi> Our Gazette (which does religiously imitate this Silence) says, The Enemies have lost Twenty thousand Men, and could scarcely <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ster Ten thousand after the Defeat;</hi> but where were <hi>Luxemburgh</hi>'s Fourscore thousand then; that they did
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97313:11"/> not entirely swallow up that Mouthful, and give us a Peace on their Terms? Is it because he would not have the War so soon at an end? Sure he is too much the King's humble Servant for that. It must then follow, that he did it not, because he could not; and seeing it is so, We have reason to fear, that the Twenty thousand slain will be found on our side: But however, it is certain that there's a terrible Butchery which has more need of an Apology than Commendation, and hath produced nothing yet, but a <hi>Te Deum.</hi> But <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> is not to be blamed: The Letter tells you, that <hi>he obeyed his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and he would rather have sacrificed all than not have done <hi>that.</hi> May God preserve us from such ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Te Deum.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another LETTER from the same Hand, on the <hi>Te Deum.</hi> Dated at <hi>Paris, Aug.</hi> 14th.</head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">IT was not without Reason that we sung <hi>Te Deum</hi> here for the last Fight, as I mentioned in my former; for according to an exact Calculation in the printed Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, we have only Two thousand Men killed, and Three or Four thousand wounded, whereas we swell the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Loss to above Twenty thousand, and those which remain are entirely defeated, and scattered, that they cease any more to be an Army. We doubted of the truth of this formerly, because other Relations gave o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Accounts; but this being published by Authority, removes all Difficulties, and confirms our staggering Faith; and indeed, how can we call the truth of it into question any more, seeing it is supported by Three or four Miracles, the least of which is sufficient to convince
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97313:11"/> the greatest Infidel? The First is, The Resurrection of many Thousand of our own Men, whom we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to Life by this Relation. It's a Thousand Pities that the <hi>Count de Montchevreuil, Prince Paul of Lorrain, and so many other brave Warriours</hi> of infinitly more worth then a croud of <hi>obscure</hi> Centinels, had not the Benefit of this Miracle. It may perhaps be answered, That they have made too much noise in the World to be conceal'd in the Resurrection of such a multitude of mean Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; but that Reason's not worth a Farthing: For here's another Miracle of an illustrious Personage on the Enemies side, who fell by the hand of death, and yet our Relation hath restored him to Life again; that is <hi>Count Solms</hi> who had his Leg shot off by a Cannon-Ball in the beginning of the Fight, and is since dead of his Wounds amongst the <hi>Allies,</hi> and his Corps carried to <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain,</hi> to be transported from thence into <hi>Holland;</hi> and yet our Relation makes him a Prisoner among us, so that the Confederates have no Reason to complain of our augmenting their Loss, since we raise their dead to life again. The Third Miracle is, That our Army hath done nothing since the Battel; for seeing we took <hi>Hay</hi> while their Army was in being, <hi>a fontiori;</hi> we ought with much more Reason, now that they are defeated, to take <hi>Liege, Louvain,</hi> and <hi>Brussels,</hi> and in our way, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy that small handful of the Enemy which is left; but it seems they have got Wings to fly, and we have none to follow, except it be by retreating towards <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren,</hi> where it is said our Army is Encamp'd, in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of a Bog, to solemnize a Triumph for the late Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. Now if this be not a Miracle, Reason is lost. But the greatest Miracle comes last, and is indeed most difficult to be comprehended, <hi>viz.</hi> That all our <hi>Conquests, and the Money which we contribute, are only for the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od of the State, and maintenance of Religion.</hi> We can very well
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97313:12"/> understand, how that all that we have despoil'd our Neighbours of, both in Peace and War, augments the King's Glory, and the Limits of his Realm, but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reckoned any thing else than a Miracle, that this War, or (much less) <hi>our League with the Turk,</hi> can any way subserve to the maintenance of Religion, except we understand <hi>the Religion of the strongest side,</hi> and if that be the case, the <hi>Allies</hi> are not very much in the wrong, to endeavour to stop its Progress in their Territories.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter from a Gentleman in <hi>Paris</hi> to his Friend in <hi>London;</hi> with an Account of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel at <hi>Landen,</hi> according to the best Information there, on the 3d. of <hi>August,</hi> being Five Days after the Battel.</head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">THE Mareschal <hi>de Luxemburgh,</hi> being willing to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Opportunity of attacking the <hi>Confederate</hi> Army, while weakned by a Detachment of 15000 Men to the <hi>French</hi> Lines, and 10000 to re-insorce <hi>Liege,</hi> did send to his Majesty for Orders to fight them, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to give them a <hi>total Overthrow.</hi> Accordingly, about Eight Days agoe, a Commission was sent him to act as he pleased. On which he gave out, That he would march for <hi>Liege:</hi> and calling a Council of War, they dislik'd the Proposal; but the Mareschal silenced them, and deceived the Enemies Spies, by telling them it was the King's Order, and so he commanded 50000 <hi>Fascines</hi> to be got ready. On the 26th. and 27th. he went to view <hi>Liege,</hi> on the 28th. the Army had Orders to march, which should have been thither as every body thought; but they were soon undeceived, when on a sudden he changed his March, and went directly toward the Enemy, hoping to surprize
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97313:12"/> them. After Nine Hours march, their Centinels dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered our Vanguard, possessing themselves of all the Avenues, to a Village called <hi>Vangrez,</hi> not far from their Front. The Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> spent the Night in drawing up his Army in Battel Array, and disposing the Order of the Attacks. The Enemy made also good use of their time, sending away their Baggage and Tents to <hi>Louvain,</hi> and casting up Intrenchments mounted with 60 Cannon, and defended by Eight Battalions of <hi>English</hi> which flankt the Trenches. About Five next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> commanded Monsieur <hi>de Montchevreuil,</hi> Lieutenant-General, and Governour of <hi>Arras,</hi> with Twentyfour Battalions, to begin the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack, and force that Village. Our Troops advanced with all imaginable Bravery, but were so warmly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Enemy, whose Cannon play'd upon them with <hi>Cartouches,</hi> and made so great slaughter, that they were oblig'd to retire in Disorder, leaving their General dead upon the Place. The Mareschal <hi>de Joyeuse</hi> who was order'd to support them, advanc'd with Twenty four other Battalions, and attackt the Enemy with such Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, that he possess'd himself of their principal Posts: but some fresh Troops coming upon him, he was beaten back with a great Slaughter; So that the Duke of <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburgh</hi> began to despair of Success; and calling on the Prince de <hi>Conti,</hi> told him, <hi>That the King's Glory depended only upon his Valour,</hi> and gave him Twentyfour fresh Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions composed of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Swisse</hi> Guards, suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Troops of the Houshold, and the Brigades of <hi>Surlaube,</hi> and <hi>Renold.</hi> The Prince fell upon the Enemy very furiously, and though he was repulsed with great Vigour, yet at the Third Charge he beat them out of their Intrenchments; and taking the Colours belonging to a Company of the Dutch Regiment of Foot-Guards, filled up the Ditch with <hi>Fascines.</hi> Being got into the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97313:13"/> Enemies Entrenchments, he put his Troops in Order of Battel, as well as the narrowness of the ground would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and fell upon the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Cuirassiers, Three Troops of the <hi>Gens d'Arms</hi> of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and the <hi>English</hi> Lifeguards lead on by the Elector of <hi>Bavaria;</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd them with so much Courage, that the Troops of the King's Houshold were forced to give ground twice, and retire behind the Brigade of <hi>Surlaube</hi> to Rally. They charg'd a Third time, and then Monsieur <hi>de Lignery</hi> who commanded them, was killed. In the mean time, the Duke <hi>de Chartres</hi> who commanded the Horse, came to re-inforce the King's Houshold: whereupon we thought that the Enemies having now lost all their advantageous Posts, could not have fail'd of receiving a total Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw; but we soon perceiv'd that they had got over the River <hi>Geete,</hi> and broken the Bridges after them, so that we could pursue them no further; our Men besides being so much harrass'd by their march the Day before, standing all Night in their Arms, and having had such a desperate Fight all that Day, that they were not able to pursue with any vigour, especially when both the Enemies Wings reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fighting, so that the Victory was wholly owing to our Numbers. We possessed our selves of their Camp, and some Artillery, but without any Baggage. The Eight English Battalions, who defended their Batteries, suffered very much. The Duke de <hi>Chartres</hi> was taken Prisoner by Four Men of that Body, and kept for Two Hours, but rescued again by some of his own Officers, and the Life Guards. The Enemy were never known to behave themselves with greater Bravery. The Duke of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> sent a short Account of the Action to the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bought Eight a Clock in his Table-Book, in these few Words, <hi>That he had obey'd his Majesty's Orders in taking</hi> Huy, <hi>and in beating the Prince of</hi> Orange. And the King rewarded Monsieur <hi>Artagnan</hi> the Bearer, with the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97313:13"/> of <hi>Arras.</hi> Our Loss is greater than that of the Enemies, especially in Officers, whereof we have not yet a true List. The greatness of our Loss is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the want of our Artillery at first, having been engaged Four Hours before we could make any use of our Cannon, by reason of a shower of Rain, which was a great hinderance to the raising of our Batteries; and however it be, it's said, That the King is not much pleas'd with the Victory.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97313:14"/>
            <head>REFLEXIONS UPON The <hi>French</hi> King's Letter; Manifesting, How He, and his Gazetteer, Contradict one another, as both of them do the Truth.</head>
            <p>THE King in his Letter to the Archbishop, to make his Victory appear Glorious indeed, tells you, <hi>That the Enemies Army consisted of their choicest Troops, in a Camp advantageously situated, and fortified with redoubtable Intrenchments, and incredible Labour; and that they foresaw</hi> Luxemburgh'<hi>s Design:</hi> Yet his Gazetteer, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph 1. 2, and 4. says, <hi>That</hi> Luxemburgh <hi>knew the Enemy to be weakned by Detachments, deceived them, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending a Design upon</hi> Liege, <hi>mustered up some Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>usands of Fascin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, the better to cover the Cheat; and that the Allies did not believe he had any D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sign upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, till the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ince of</hi> Orange, <hi>as they are pleas'd to call him, and the Elector of</hi> Bavaria <hi>took Horse, and discovered it, when the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Guards came in view;</hi> which mightily derogates from the Glory of <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Victory: For this is a plain Confession That they took Advantage of us when weakest, did in a manner surprize us, and give us no time to make <hi>redo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Intrenchments;</hi> but whether <hi>Louis</hi> XIV. or the <hi>Abbé Renadaut,</hi> his Gazetteer, be in the Right, let them deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97313:14"/> it betwixt them, as also, whether the Abbot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves not to have his Pension curtail'd, for publishing his Lies with so little Precaution.</p>
            <p>The King in his Letter tells us, <hi>That part of the Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Army was slain in the Field, part was drown'd in the Flight, and the rest were dispersed.</hi> Yet the Gazetteer, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph 38 says, <hi>That Twelve of our Battalions, and Three of our Squadrons, escap'd without so much as being once charg'd;</hi> so that the Abbot contradicts his Master again, in saying they were all dispersed; for so many Battalions and Squadrons, will merit the name of a Body.</p>
            <p>But further, We may observe on the King's Letter, that it was no less than Nine Days after the Battel before it was writ, which may justly fill us with Wonder, that <hi>Louis,</hi> XIV. who is so ambitious of his Glory, should have conceal'd so long from his Subjects, the Particulars of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, which did so much advance it: but the Reason is explain'd by the Author of the private Letter from <hi>Paris,</hi> they <hi>knew not whether to mourn, or to rejoyce, the case appear'd so doubtful;</hi> and in truth, by the King, and the Abbots justling together in their Advice, it would seem they were but then beginning to recover from their surprize, and therefore no wonder they should stagger. However the <hi>Subjects wanted a Cordial,</hi> or perhaps a <hi>powerful dissuasive from a Revolt,</hi> and therefore <hi>Louis</hi> emits his Letter, which <hi>thunders</hi> upon his Enemies in the <hi>Front,</hi> but <hi>fawns</hi> upon them and his Subjects both in the <hi>Rear,</hi> and modestly protests, That he desires nothing more <hi>than the happiness of the Last,</hi> and a <hi>solid and durable Peace with the First;</hi> so that by <hi>Louis</hi>'s own Confession, the <hi>latter</hi> depends on the <hi>former;</hi> and that he might drive the Argument as far as it would go, he tells us, That he hath always of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Peace to his Enemies, <hi>even in the midst of his greatest Prosperities;</hi> a fair Confession <hi>that his good Luck is now on the Declension,</hi> Then where's all the Glory of this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97313:15"/> Victory? But that this Letter was calculated on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to keep up the Spirits of his disheartned Subjects, will appear plain enough, by the manifest Falshoods which it so confidently advances; as, That the Confederate Army was totally dispersed, when he himself did acknowledge, That the Prince of <hi>Orange retreated like Turenne,</hi> and could not be ignorant of both the Wings drawing off in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that before the Date of this Letter, the Confederates were at least as strong, as on the Day of Battel; and had, by their own Confession, Twenty five thousand Men at <hi>Liege,</hi> and under the Duke of <hi>Wirtemberg.</hi> Which <hi>Lewis</hi> knowing to be true, thinks fit to join Prayers with his Praises, and therefore <hi>demands a Peace from God, tho' he pretends already to have it in his own Power to give.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then as for his Pensioner <hi>Abbot,</hi> let's Examine his <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Relation.</hi> In his Fifteenth Article he says, That our Infantry was drawn behind an Intrenchment, and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain'd by our Horse. Whereas he told us in the Fourth, That our Army was drawn up in Battel Array, at the Head of our Camp; which was the Truth, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to our own Gazette, which gave the First Account of the <hi>Action, as also to the</hi> Relation printed in <hi>Holland,</hi> and re-printed here with the Plane of the Battel. In the Third Paragraph he says indeed, That part of our Foot were posted behind the Intrenchments, which were cast up <hi>because the Ground was open;</hi> so little Reason had <hi>Louis</hi> to magnifie his Victory, because of our <hi>advantageous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to the Abbot, he says, Art. 16. That the Cannon began to play on both sides by Four in the Morning; whereas the private Letter says, That they were engaged Four Hours before they could make use of their Cannon: And the Dutch Relation above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, says almost the same.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97313:15"/>
            <p>The Abbot in Art. 13. says, The Allies fortified themselves all the Night long, with great diligence, having mounted their Trenches with Eighty Pieces of Cannon, Art. 19. That they were beat from <hi>Nerwinde</hi> with great Vigour, and re-took it after a long and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Fight; That the French took it a Second time, and were again beat off to the utmost Hedges; and that the like befell those who attacked <hi>Laer.</hi> Art. 20. That <hi>Praconta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Montrevil,</hi> were beat back from the Plain, and oblig'd to retire after many Charges. Art. 26. That the <hi>Gens d'Arms,</hi> and Troops of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shold, were obliged to retire under the Fire of their Infantry, to Rally; and that the Duke <hi>de Chartres</hi> was surrounded (he ought to have said Prisoner) and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Men killed, and Art. 31. That the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates made many obstinate Charges against their whole Cavalry. Then if it be so, as the Abbot says, that we were strongly intrench'd with Eighty Pieces of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non before us, and repulsed the French four or five times at least, after many Charges in the several Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts; I appeal to any Man of Common Sense, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it hath the least Shadow of Probability, that the French should not lose above Two thousand Men, when their Battalions and Squadrons were so often repuls'd, and had Fourscore Cannon thundring upon them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides small Fire-Arms, from Five in the Morning till near Five in the Evening, as he owns himself in one of his Gazetts.</p>
            <p>Nor is he less unhappy in diminishing their own Loss, than he is in augmenting ours: For Art. 40. he says, That <hi>All</hi> the Advices from the Enemy's Country, make their Loss to exceed Twenty thousand, which is a manifest Untruth. No printed Advices, (and I hope they may pass for <hi>some)</hi> did ever affirm any such thing; but as for what Intelligences he may receive
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97313:16"/> from the French Spies, and his fellow Pensioners from the Confederates Country, I know no body will think themselves oblig'd to believe them, but those who pay for them, and would have them to be true. But he may easily be convinc'd of the Improbability of this himself, if he will be pleased to consider his own 37th. Article, where he mentions only, that the Confederates were pursued to the River <hi>Geete,</hi> and will also observe how near to their Camp the said River was by his own Relation, together with the Note in the <hi>Private Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, That the toil of the March, and fatigue of the Battel, rendred the French unfit to pursue, if they could have pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the River</hi> Geete. But to conclude this Point. I know nothing better to demonstrate the Impossibility of the French's having <hi>so little,</hi> and we so <hi>great a Loss,</hi> as the <hi>Abbot</hi> says, than to view and consider the Plane of the Battel, and the situation of our Camp, as engraven in the above-mention'd Relation beyond Sea, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed here by Mr. <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Harris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then for the Abbot's Conclusion, That the taking of <hi>Heidelberg, Roses,</hi> and <hi>Huy,</hi> his Advantage over the <hi>Streights Fleet,</hi> and the gaining of this Battel, are Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God's having always own'd the Justice of his Master's Arms; <hi>Careat successibus opto quisquis ab even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu facta notanda putet.</hi> It seems he has forgot that since the beginning of this War, his Master hath been beat out of <hi>Rhemeberg, Keyserswart, Bonne</hi> and <hi>Ments;</hi> that his Troops were defeated in the Diocess of <hi>Cologne,</hi> by the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and in <hi>Flanders,</hi> at <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court,</hi> by the English and Dutch: that he hath totally lost his footing in <hi>Ireland;</hi> his Partisans are wholly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued in <hi>Scotland:</hi> that his <hi>Royal Sun</hi> was eclipsed at <hi>La Hogue;</hi> and that his Troops were beat off from before <hi>Rhinefield</hi> and <hi>Liege:</hi> So that by the Abbot's Argument, his Master's Arms were not engag'd in a <hi>just War then,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97313:16"/> and he will have need of all his Philosophy to prove it <hi>juster now:</hi> But farther, He would do well to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that <hi>Pignerol</hi> is besieged, <hi>Belgrade</hi> invested, King <hi>William</hi> at the Head of a formidable Army, as well as his Allies, Prince <hi>Louis,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Savoy;</hi> that their Privateering Fleet dares not make Head against ours at Sea, and that the decisive Blow is not yet gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; so that he had not best sing the Triumph before the Victory, nor feed himself so much with the hopes of seeing his Masters Glory encreased, and his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons enlarged, who adores <hi>Venus,</hi> and <hi>Debauches his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> while the <hi>God of War</hi> destroys their Lords, of which Latter, the <hi>Parisian,</hi> are so sensible, that the very next Day after the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> a Paper was found upon <hi>Louis</hi>'s Statue, in the place of <hi>Victoire,</hi> representing him with the Words of his Predecessor <hi>Louis</hi> XII. in his Mouth, after the News of his Victory at <hi>Ravenna,</hi> where the best of his Officers fell on the Spot. <hi>Would to God</hi> (said he with a deep sigh) <hi>that I had lost the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, so my brave Captains were alive; and may my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies have always such Victories, where the Vanquish'd are victorious, and the Conquerors overcome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will it appear unreasonable for <hi>Louis</hi> XIV. to express himself thus, if we consider the Account gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by a Person of no less Honour than Lieutenant-General <hi>Scravenmore,</hi> That Twelve hundred wounded French Officers were brought into <hi>Namur,</hi> while he was Prisoner there, and Four hundred of them died e're he came a way; which doth also demonstrate the Falshood of the Abbot's Relation, that they have not lost above Two thousand Men, Four hundred Officers dead of their Wounds, and Eight hundred still in the Surgeons hands, bear proportion to a much greater number of slain: and besides, we have no Account yet, how many French Officers were slain in the Field, nor
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97313:17"/> how many are dead, and under Cure in other Places, as at <hi>Mons, Maubeuge, Dinant,</hi> and other Frontier Towns, which there is no Reason to doubt would quickly swell to Two thousand; so that it seems the French Officers fought All, and their Souldiers None; but it's well for the last, if they have found it so.</p>
            <p>One word for our <hi>Protestant Jacobites,</hi> and then I have done. On all Occasions they magnifie the Vera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the <hi>Paris Gazetteer,</hi> and therefore I hope they believe him now; and if so, pray let them reconcile <hi>the Interest of the Protestant Religion,</hi> which they profess, <hi>with the Interest</hi> of that which he averrs, <hi>is the French King's Design to maintain, by enlarging his Conquests:</hi> But let them understand this as they please, I think we are beholding to him for such a piece of Ingenuity, or rather for speaking so much Truth at unawares. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we have hence a very fair Warning what we are to expect, if the late King should ever be re-established by the French King's Power: For he has assured his Subjects, on the word of his Abbot, that they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the <hi>Augmentation of his own Glory and Limits, and the Maintenance of Religion;</hi> which is, in plain English, That he will establish his own Tyranny, and Popish Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, where-ever he can. Then seeing the Case is so, We know not what to think of those Mens Zeal for the Protestant Religion, who wish for his Success on any Pretence whatsoever.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>